In the lives of servitors
En la vida de sirvientes
we have to also deal with our past or …
también tenemos que lidiar con nuestro pasado , o...
what’s sometimes called prārabdha-karma.
lo que en ocasiones es llamado prārabdha-karma.
[Conventional Suffering | Escaping Illusion]
[Sufrimiento Convencional | Escapar de la Ilusión]
The karma that you are stuck with in this life, that you generated.
El karma con el que estás atorado en esta vida, el que tú generas.
We generated this particular body
Hemos generado este cuerpo en particular
and karmic circumstances
y las circunstancias kármicas
before coming in connection with Kṛṣṇa consciousness.
antes de entrar en contacto con la Consciencia de Kṛṣṇa.
So it has so much karmic destiny in play.
Así que está en juego mucho del destino kármico.
Then someone comes in connection with Kṛṣṇa consciousness.
Entonces se conecta con la Consciencia de Kṛṣṇa,
Rūpa Gosvāmī says in Bhakti-rasāmṛta-sindhu,
Rūpa Gosvāmī dice en el Bhakti-rasāmṛta-sindhu,
kleśa-ghnī śubha-dā mokṣa- laghutā-kṛt su-durlabhā
kleśa-ghnī śubha-dā mokṣa- laghutā-kṛt su-durlabhā
sāndrānanda-viśeṣātmā śrī-kṛṣṇākarṣiṇī ca sā [Brs: 1.1.17]
sāndrānanda-viśeṣātmā śrī-kṛṣṇākarṣiṇī ca sā (Brs: 1.1.17)
He’s outlining what is kṛṣṇa-bhakti substantially,
Está subrayando lo que substancialmente es kṛṣṇa-bhakti
and what is the outcome
y lo que produce
or what are symptoms, what are side-effects,
o los síntomas y las repercusiones,
what is the outcome.
qué se produce.
Everything is being taken into consideration
Todo se toma en consideración,
beginning with kleśa-ghnī.
empezando con kleśa-ghnī.
Saying, the suffering,
Es decir, el sufrimiento,
the conventional suffering that’s associated
el sufrimiento convencional que se la asocia
with being embodied, prārabdha-karma,
con el estar encarnado prārabdha-karma,
your accumulated karma in this life,
acumulas karma en esta vida,
he says, “It will put an end to that.”
él dice, "pondrá un final a eso."
Now, people will think, “Oh, but what we see, you know ...
Ahora, la gente piensa, "Oh, pero lo que vemos, ya sabes...
Devotees are suffering in different ways.”
los devotos están sufriendo en distintas formas".
There is not like ever you come in connection with Kṛṣṇa consciousness,
No es como que entras en conexión con la Consciencia de Kṛṣṇa
and then you never get the flu again, you know …
y ya nunca vuelves a tener catarro, ya sabes...
When Gurudev was riding on the train,
Cuando Gurudev viajaba en el tren,
he would go from Navadvīp to Calcutta
íbamos desde Navadvīp a Calcutta
in service to Śrīla Guru Mahārāj,
sirviendo a Śrīla Guru Mahārāj,
when he was Gaurendu Brahmachārī,
cuando era Gaurendu Bramachārī,
and just like people in the modern times,
Y tal como la gente en los tiempos modernos,
they might say to us, “Oh”, you know, “the Hare Kṛṣṇa;
Nos pueden decir. "Oh", ya sabes, "los Hare Kṛṣṇa;
there was a Hare Kṛṣṇa on the train.”
Había un Hare Kṛṣṇa; en el tren".
These are Bengalis, and so at that time
Estos son lo bengalies y en ese entonces
they called them, you know, ‘gaurāṅgas’.
ellos les llamaban, ya sabes, ‘gaurāṅgas’.
So, they like, “Hey, gaurāṅga!
Así que ellos decían, “¡Oye, gaurāṅga!
We wanna talk to the gaurāṅga.”
Queremos hablar al gaurāṅga.”
And then, and they are talking to Gurudev—
Y entonces, ellos estaban hablando con Gurudev—
at the time he is Gaurendu Brahmachārī—
en aquel entonces él era Gaurendu Bramachari—
and they are saying,
y decían,
“If devotees … they are supposed to be liberated,
"Si los devotos... se supone que están liberados,
how come we see that they get sick?
¿cómo es que vemos que se enferman?
Rather … and really they should be free from any sort of disease
Más bien... y de verdad deberían estar libres de enfermedad
and just always be healthy.
y estar siempre saludables.
You know, why should they be
Tú sabes, ¿porqué habrían de estar
in an unhealthy, a diseased condition or any such thing?”
en una condición poco saludable o enferma o alguna de esas cosas?
And Gurudev answered by saying, he said,
Y Gurudev contestaba diciendo, él decía,
“No, just the opposite”,
"No, justamente lo opuesto",
he said, “because the devotees, they are escaping māyā,
decía, "porque los devotos están escapando de māyā,
they’re on the way out of the material world,
Se están yendo del mundo material,
so they should be attacked with many varieties of things.”
así que tienen que ser atacados con mucha clase de cosas."